DVG

D.V. Gundappa, popularly known as DVG was more a phenomenon than an individual. There is a saying in English – “Some write books on history, but some others create history”. DVG belonged to the latter category. Born in a Tamil family on 17th March, 1887 in a predominantly Telugu region - Mulabagal in Kolar District of Karnataka – he was a very great scholar in Sanskrit and English. There is a saying in Kannada that there is no leaf which the goat does not touch. There is no subject on which DVG has not written. It is said about Oliver Goldsmith that there was nothing he touched which he did not adorn. DVG’s works are innumerable to be even mentioned in a short note like this. However, just a few must be mentioned to understand the stature of this intellectual giant. He has written five biographies, among them two on Vidyaranya (1983), eight Memoirs, among them one on Artists (1970), one on Literature creators (1970), one on the Dewans of Mysore (1971) and one on Vaidic traditionalists (1972), two works on Children’s literature, four works on nonfiction prose. His interest in Drama and Theatre resulted in the writing seven plays, among them the translation of Shakespeare’s Macbeth (1936, 1974). His works on religion are a special category by themselves – Purusha Sukta (1953, 1971), Isopanishat (1953, 1970) Bhagavadgita Tatparya (1966, 1971), God (1973) and Rita, Satya, Dharma (1975). He has to his credit fifteen collections of poems, among them Nivedana (1924, 1933, 1956), Vidyaranya Stuti (1924) Antahpura Gite (1950, 1953), Valmiki Vyasa Vandanam (1951), Gita Shakuntalam (1960, 1961) etc. However, two of his very special works are Manku Thimmana Kagga & Marula Muniyana Kagga. Many scholars think that his Manku Thimmana Kagga which has seen many editions (1943, 1950, 1958, 1964, 1969, 1987 et al) is his magnum opus. However, it is his most popular work and there are many who can recite it from the beginning to the end as they do the Bhagavadgita. There are as many as twenty scholarly works of comment and criticism on it. The English translations of Mankuthimmana Kagga by Sri. D. Seshagiri Rao and Sri. A. Narasimha Bhat who have also translated DVG’s Marula Muniyana Kagga and the six Audio Cassettes by Swami Brahmananda must be specially mentioned. The best Kannada critics have written books and articles on DVG Among them, Professor L.S. Seshagiri Rao, C.N. Mangala, T.N. Padmanabhan, G.S. Chakravarthi, P. Balakrishna Rao and G.P. Rajarathnam. “A special mention must be made of Shatavadhani Dr. R. Ganesh who is an authority on DVG and he has made a special study of the metrical experiments in DVG’s poetry. It may not out of place to mention here that DVG was quite a “Personality”.“A very impressive figure, a wonderful and witty conversationalist, a dominating “presence” in any company, a lover of life with great zest and zeal, he gave assurance of a complete man. The tradition he belonged to – the great scholar Govinda Pai, the translation pioneer B.M. Srikantaiah, the students’ pet T.S. Venkannaiah, A.R. Krishna Sastry of Prabuddha Karnataka, the charismatic orator C.K. Venkataramaiah and my own teacher, V. Sitaramaiah.”

-S. Ramaswamy
Fellow, Silliman College,
Yale University, USA

Larger Goal

Young men, life is before you. Two voices are calling you – one coming out from the swamps of selfishness and force, where success means death and the other from hilltops of justice and progress, where even failure brings glory. Two lights are seen in your horizon – one, the fast fading marsh light of power, and the other slowly rising sun of human brotherhood. Two ways lie open for you – one leading to an even lower and lower plain, where are heard the cries of despair and the curses of the poor, where manhood shrivels and possession rots down the possessor; and the other leading to the highlands of the morning, where are heard the glad shouts of humanity and where honest effort is rewarded with immortality.

-John P. Altgeld

Is there a larger goal in life? – Yes says the Saint Kanakadasa. We all pray with our heart and soul to the Person residing in the higher abode (God) for salvation, with devotion for one’s satisfaction, strengthen the soul and attain eternal happiness.

The above goals are much different than basic goals of getting food and shelter but need to coexist with them. Divinity, Soul, Devotion, Happiness belong to only human beings and not for other animals. Humanity arises therefore because of such a higher purpose in life.

Saint Kanakadasa in that aspect was fortunate as his hunger to basic needs was very small and could be fulfilled by hunting or farming. He was a person who had learnt music & literature and had realized his supreme God through this. He could attain happiness by singing prayers. Can we be in the same state or get to that? As he had complete faith in Lord Keshava (Krishna) do we have faith in any other subject? Like his goal was happiness through devotion, what is our goal? Goal is one of the forms of goodness.

What do we mean by Good?

All of us desire good things in Life. Everyone aspires for good conduct. What do we mean by good? What is good? Does whatever appears beautiful and sweet is all those good? For some, taste of liquor is sweet. Some like face which has been artificially made up with the use of cosmetics and goggles. So, can we conclude that this is goodness? What might appeal to us at one moment may look distasteful after sometime. Food that we consume out of lot of liking may actually be rendered tasteless after we are saturated with its consumption. What will decide the goodness of our likes and dislikes? What are the attributes of goodness and what is its form?

Origin of Good or Goodness – is having the right or desirable quality. In Sanskrit the equivalent of good is Sat ()-the ideal; pure and true essence (nature) of an entity or existence in the Vedanta or alternatively or something that is eternal.

Sat in the context of Gita can be identified in Chapter 17, verses 26-27 as

sad-bhave sadhu-bhave ca
sad ity etat prayujyaet
prasaste karmani tatha
sac-chabdah partha yujyate
yajne tapasi dane ca
sthitih sad iti cocyate
karma caiva tad-arthiyam
sad ity evabhidhiyate

The concept is also famously expressed in a mantra found in the Brihadaranyaka Upanishad (1.3.28),

Asato mâ sad gamaya / tamaso mâ jyotir gamaya /
mrtyor mâ amrutam gamaya

“Lead me from delusion to truth; from darkness to light; from mortality to immortality”

Sat has been adapted as: sattva “purity” and satya “truth”.

A quality or feature which remains unaffected by the boundary of region and remains unchanged with reference to time can be referenced as being good. In other words a universally acceptable and agreed character can be termed as good. Above all this, the main characteristic of goodness is one that is eternal and can remain unaffected in its form.

Then what in our world can remain forever? All that is recognizable by our senses is changing constantly and almost in real-time. All objects living and non-living keep getting created and destroyed. In this mortal world what can be recognized and accepted as immortal?

All our great saints prophase that God is the only truth and eternal. Holy men and spiritual leaders in all countries and in all religions have believed that God is the only truth and does not undergo deformity. Every second innumerable changes are taking place in the world and beyond all this is hidden some supreme energy. This energy is residing in earth, sky, inanimate and animate objects of this universe working and controlling all acts from behind as the unquestionable Emperor. This supreme energy is God, Divinity, Supreme soul and Goodness. There is nothing other than this which can be considered as good.

That conduct, that realization, that practice and finally that experience which leads us to realization of this energy is Goodness. Any other thing which can obstruct this process can be termed as bad or evil. There is one God but his names and forms are innumerable. Likewise Goodness has only one definition and is one philosophy, its forms and effects are different.

Based on this, our sages have determined what is good and what is bad and this goodness has been called as noble character.

Our Purpose

The game of life requires all one’s energy to play it at one’s best. The present gives us the only chance we have for doing. To use it in futile grief or regret is to leave something worthwhile undone, indulge in something that does no one any good and interferes with maintaining a cheerful spirit that brings happiness to self and to others.

-Samuel Fessenden Clarke

For our life to be fruitful and meaningful there is greater necessity to have knowledge of right goal and means to achieve it. The purpose of this book is to help charter a map which can be supportive in this journey of life. This thought and exercise is not of the easy order. Our great ancestors have no doubt left behind valuable directions in this regard but where does it stand in the era where newer technologies and science are evolving daily, newer religions and factions are getting formed and our mind is constantly getting dragged in innumerable directions shaking the established faith of life. In this technologically advanced environment we have to reexamine our challenges in life.

This book is not aimed at scholars but written with intention to reach out to large class of common people. Life as a whole is beyond the capabilities of human language and the roots of life’s experiences is much deeper than the root of knowledge.

To those scholarly readers there could be many questions that arise during the course of reading, I request you to continue reading till the end and then make a review of this writing.

The author’s second request is this writing is not an instant solution to your current challenges in life. Man’s life is vast and inexplicable to be captured in few words. I would rather not dare to say that through this I will be able to help you establish your purpose of life in one shot. The philosophy and premise of this book is many fold. It would be more appropriate to call it as mind’s inclination, behavior and occupation rather than philosophy.

As the breadth and length of the river get larger we would require more channels and pillars to build the bridge, so is the case with our life where our intellect and mind needs to take different forms to meet its challenges. Our life is a daily fight and we need to have practiced various techniques to emerge victorious. One leg is inadequate to walk and one hand is not enough for our work. Just like that one, philosophy alone doesn't suffice to stay productive in this life. This does not anyway suggest that there is something greater that will be revealed here. The attempt that is being made here is also not something that is outstanding, not a difficult one and nor challenging. To make our life self satisfactory and meaningful one we do not require some special books, we need few simple formulae which can be comprehended by us and strongly hold on to those by practicing them. The best example to such a life is that of Mahatma Gandhi. He was not a great scholar nor did he research on great works, all that he did was to have belief in few principles and live by it with higher dedication to make it fruitful. Whatever may be our philosophy or fundamental principles the key to success lies in strong belief and following it with higher commitment? It is futile to having read great works by great scholars and unable to inculcate and emulate any of them in our daily lives.

If we need to see improvement in state of our fellow beings then there needs to be a change in their thought process. For this the mind has to transform itself, as unless this transformation takes place none of the others can change for better.

Three Main Characteristics

First and foremost is the devotion to life has to increase. Life is a larger object and living is an art. To lead a good life is neither a sin nor act of shame. The philosophy “To make life good and lead that in the most purposeful manner is our duty” should be deep rooted in our minds and heart. That is progress. Progress simply means upward movement in life or having a right goal and moving towards achieving it.

What is right or good has been the question that is addressed to a certain extent. For now let us consider all those actions accepted and acknowledged, which lead to better state of life as right or good.

Secondly, faith in human efforts has to increase tremendously among our fellow human beings. In the most challenging situations one has the ability to discover what is good and how to achieve that. To know that duty and put all the efforts with strength and wisdom is what is called for. Such courageous character needs to be firm in our people’s minds. Science is a result of this progressive evolution and in turn is responsible for further progress.

Thirdly, our daily conduct needs to be filled with sweet and friendly radiance. Humility and goodness in our conduct needs to be natural rather than that is arising out of fear towards law, society or religious institution. Good conduct should have developed because of thoughtful alliance to such characters instead of blind faith.

Therefore, there is need for strong inculcation of three characters : a) Enthusiasm towards Life b) Human Efforts and c) Social Network. Practical application of these are i) Progress ii) Science and iii) Humility respectively. A wholehearted belief in the above is the necessary preparation for enabling growth of civilization.

Present Living

Aren’t people living like this today? Yes, they are but it is insipid and half hearted in approach. It is directionless and following herd instinct without a definitive purpose. It also appears to be unscientific, unenthusiastic and lacking any courageous act.

Our life is being led very mechanically lacking independent review of it and giving it a lack luster appearance. A true life should resemble that of a plant not that of a machine. Plant has everyday fresh life with new sprouts, buds and flowers. Likewise our lives need to be radiating daily with new activities and accomplishments than appearing dull and boring. If we are not breathing freshness to our life through our individual efforts and thinking, it is as good as we are dead.

The irony of our country today is any one we meet is constantly talking about god, holy men, holy scriptures, supreme energy, being truthful and non-violence but is completely absent in their actions and practices. This leaves us with irreconcilable situation between our speech and conduct. Why is there such a disconnect?

If we look geographically India is blessed to have vast land which is fertile, abundant natural resources, long coastal lines and more importantly large population with majority of people having reasonable intelligence that can be put into use.

In spite of this, we are having sizeable population still living below the poverty line, many households suffering from chronic diseases and people who are clueless about tomorrow’s living. On one hand we are talking about economic progress being made through growth of service industries but unable to bring in innovation and take advantage of it, we are marketing medical tourism but unable to provide adequate healthcare system to needy. All this leads us to when and how do we become self-reliant and strong?

Voice of Great Saints

Among all the works that have been in the world, Vedas have been recognized as the most ancient work. We do not get any indication of a fragile and weak mind but on the contrary it clearly voices strength, courage and determination. The prayers rendered by the great saints during this period is as follows: “Oh God! We need to live, provide us with longevity, let our ears keep hearing the most auspicious things, let our tongue taste the most delicious food, let our minds be brimming with enthusiasm, let our speech be strong, let our intellect be vibrant, let we have the best physical ability, let our enemies loose and flee, let our wealth grow and let the productivity of food and cows increase. Oh god! Let you be served by us hundreds of years with rejoice and happiness, let us get adequate rain at right times, let the productivity of field increase, let us not get affected by diseases, give us objects of enjoyment”. Such was the Aryan race’s enthusiasm towards life, self-confidence, aspiration to be victorious; they never exhibited any signs of despair, frustration and disinterest. They always considered adventurous journey filled with energy and courage.

Our ancestors such a thought process does not mean they did not have challenges in life. In midst of such prayers they always witnessed natural disasters, atrocious human behavior, fear of enemies, loss of hope, poverty, illness, separation and death. At one end there was birth of life’s aspirations in different forms and at the other end there was accumulation of difficulties and hardships. At this juncture Holy Scriptures of India (Vedas) originated. What lies at the inner crest of our life? What lies beyond that is visible to our human eyes? What is there inside each of us? Where is the food for this river called life? Who holds the strings and controls spring of energy that is seen in our life? Where does the Sun come from? How are seasons controlled? What is death and what lies beyond it? – These are the questions that might have posed for a very long time on which human minds have debated and the result of which is seen as the summary of Upanishads.

Such debates continued for a fairly long time and in the process gave birth to different religions. Some people believed and declared rituals and sacrifices as supreme. Some of them considered customs and practices to be great and while some others meditation and penance. Few considered family and charity as greater and others detachment from social system. There was also those believed in each of the above philosophies and considered them to have individual significance based on place and time.

Fallacies of Vedanta

This world is creation of Brahma and is completely under his influence, every living being in its primary form is a reflection of Brahman, if man lives with wisdom it might be possible for him to realize this higher form, purposeful living with right thinking is good and not bad has been preached in Upanishads. But this preaching never got into hearts and minds of common people. All works of Sri Adi Shankaracharya are in Sanskrit. All works which originated later can be grouped into a) works of scholars and b) works of commoners. Works of scholars were in Sanskrit and that of the commoners were in the colloquial languages such as Hindi, Kannada, Bengali, Tamil, Telugu etc. The differences in these two groups of works are not at the level of language but in the nature of its subject. Scholarly embellished works were based on the commentaries of Shankaracharya or others; they were logically oriented, grammatically correct and meaningfully presented. There are few works which claim as the exact thoughts of Sri Adi Shankaracharya and few others which decry the same and argue against it. In response to this there are few which reclaim the first one and others which recommends denial of what Sri Adi Shankarcharya has proposed. Likewise we can find innumerable arguments in favor and against which are logically based.

In the texts of commoners we find more discussion on as to which of the above thought process or philosophies is more sacred. This human body is dry log of wood, why such ornamentation to this body, attachments to wife and children is like a puppet show, why such interest and dedication to them, world is but an illusion, life is a bubble, to claim human effort is exaggeration everything is fate driven and determined by our past actions, happiness is a dream, beauty is a mirage and it is futile to put efforts in this context. One cannot escape from what fate brings and one cannot create which is not in our fate.

Janma dukham jara dukham, jaaya dukham punah punaha !
Samsara saagaram dukham, Sarvam dukhamayam jagath !!

This Vedanta is downtrodden and helpless. The songs sung by holy disciples of Hari and Shiva, historical stories narrated enumerating and effecting tears in eyes of listeners are all in praise of such misery laden detachment. People who have been canvassing such a philosophy have failed to remember that by making such an argument we are just accusing the creator. People who are at all times experiencing hardships develop liking towards such philosophy as they get some comfort in the words expressed there. To escape from this ocean of difficulties the only path is through fasting. One has to ill treat his body, chant hymns of god, sacrificing the world, not eat stomach full and not earn enough to completely once miseries. This is reaching to a stage where one is living life of half dead unable to leave life completely and unable to commit suicide. They constantly chant to end their life.

Natural Sciences

Science can be mainly classified as i) Natural Sciences ii) Social Science.

In science, the term natural science refers to a naturalistic approach to the study of the universe, which is understood as obeying rules or laws of natural origin. It encompasses everything from human life to study of stars and planets. It helps us to analyze the formation, fundamental composition, principles of each object and its behavior towards other objects. To appreciate the capabilities of this we need to here recollect and name few of the accomplishments from it:

All forms of transportation vehicles – land, air and water.
Electricity and innumerable electrical appliances.
Communication from Telegraph to the latest mobile gadgets.
Photography and all its advancements in cinematography.
Early form of printing press to the latest technologies in printing and publishing.
Metallurgy, Application of fuels.
Fertilizers and latest farming equipment.
Traditional medicines to latest devices and drugs for Healthcare.
Surgical Techniques and Equipment for curing the most complicated medical disorders.
Glass and it’s varied application from ornamentation to safety.
Carbon and its application.
Weapons and Military Technologies.
Power generation Equipment – Thermal, Nuclear, Solar Panels, Windmills.
Microscope, Telescope and innumerable optical devices.
Latest advancements in Information Technology Internet Revolution and its impact on communication.
Biotechnology.

The list can go on endlessly and science has impacted mankind to a large extent in every sphere of life and it is unlikely that today an individual is unaffected by at least one of them. All such advancements in Science and Technology have fostered and helped creation of God. Are we in a position to refute this statement?

There could be few of them which have been put to use by certain section of people in favor of personal greed rather than helping mankind. But, where doesn’t such a personal greed exist; we have seen them in few saints, so called holy men and spiritual gurus. This does not mean all the saints; holy men and spiritual teachers can be defamed. Isn’t earning livelihood one’s duty? Is there harm in working and earning for one’s livelihood? The important thing here is about work and not about livelihood. Father of physics Newton; English naturalist and propose of theory of evolution Charles Darwin; pioneer of antiseptic surgery Joseph Lister; French Chemist and microbiologist Louis Pasteur; Scottish inventor and mechanical engineer James Watt; inventor of spinning frame Richard Arkwright; inventor of telegraph Thomas Alva Edison and many such people have used their intellect to serve human society and in process have worshipped God.

Today, natural sciences are more commonly divided into life sciences, such as botany and zoology; and physical sciences, which include physics, chemistry, geology and astronomy.

Physics

Physics embodies the study of the fundamental constituents of the universe, the forces and interactions they exert on one another, and the results produced by these interactions. In general, physics is regarded as the fundamental science, because all other natural sciences use and obey the principles and laws set down by the field. Physics relies heavily on mathematics as the logical framework for formulation and quantification of principles.

Key historical developments in physics include Isaac Newton’s theory of universal gravitation and classical mechanics, an understanding of electricity and its relation to magnetism, Einstein’s theories of special and general relativity, the development of thermodynamics, and the quantum mechanical model of atomic and subatomic physics The field of physics. is extremely broad, and can include such diverse studies as quantum mechanics and theoretical physics, applied physics and optics.

Chemistry

Constituting the scientific study of matter at the atomic and molecular scale, chemistry deals primarily with collections of atoms, such as gases, molecules, crystals, and metals. The composition, statistical properties, transformations and reactions of these materials are studied. Chemistry also involves understanding the properties and interactions of individual atoms for use in larger-scale applications. Some of the useful applications of this have been in manufacturing of drugs, fertilizers, dyes and paints.

Biology

This field encompasses a set of disciplines that examines phenomena related to living organisms. The scale of study can range from subcomponent biophysics up to complex ecologies.

Biology is concerned with the characteristics, classification and behaviors of organisms, as well as how species were formed and their interactions with each other and environment.

The biological fields of botany, zoology, and medicine date back to early periods of civilization, while microbiology was introduced in the 17th century with the invention of the microscope.

Earth Science

Earth science (also known as geosciences), is an all-embracing term for the sciences related to the planet Earth, including geology, geophysics, hydrology, meteorology, physical geography, oceanography, and soil science.

Earth sciences today are closely linked to climate research and the petroleum and mineral exploration industries.

Engineering

Engineering is the discipline, art, skill and profession of acquiring and applying scientific, mathematical, economic, social, and practical knowledge to design and build structures, machines, devices, systems, materials and processes that safely realize improvements to the lives of people.

Medicine

Medicine is the science and art of healing. It encompasses a variety of health care practices evolved to maintain and restore health by the prevention and treatment of illness.

Contemporary medicine applies health science, biomedical research, and medical technology to diagnose and treat injury and disease, typically through medication, surgery, or some other form of therapy.

Even people who are residing in the rural areas are completely cognizant of the benefits of the mankind has derived from the above disciplines.

Social Science

Let us now look at Social Science. The Social Sciences are the fields of scholarship that study society. “Social Science” is commonly used as an umbrella term to refer to a plurality of fields outside of the natural sciences.

These include: anthropology, archaeology, business administration, criminology, economics, geography, linguistics, political science, sociology, international relations, communication, and, in some contexts, history, law, and psychology.

a) Political Science- What do we understand by a State and what do we understand by its Government, what are the components of it; what should be the relation between government and its citizens; duties of government; reaction of public to wrong doings of the government; inter-state relationships; where is the main strength of the government; how should the system be structured if the government is to be likeable by its citizens. Political science also studies power in international relations and the theory of Great powers and Superpowers.

b) Economics - Economics is a social science that seeks to analyze and describe the production, distribution, and consumption of wealth. Economics has two broad branches: microeconomics, where the unit of analysis is the individual agent, such as a household or firm, and macroeconomics, where the unit of analysis is an economy as a whole.

c) Treasury (Rajyakosha) – It deals with income and expenditure with respect to government. It includes various taxes, duties, levies and such other.

d) Currency (Control and Production) - In economics, currency refers to a generally accepted medium of exchange. These are usually the coins and banknotes of a particular government, which comprise the physical aspects of a nation’s money supply. The other part of a nation’s money supply consists of bank deposits (sometimes called deposit money), ownership of which can be transferred by means of cheques, debit cards, or other forms of money transfer. Deposit money and currency are money in the sense that both are acceptable as a means of payment. Money in the form of currency has predominated in human civilizations from about 10,000 BCE. In most cases, each private central bank has monopoly control over the supply and production of its own currency. To facilitate trade between these currency zones, there are different exchange rates, which are the prices at which currencies (and the goods and services of individual currency zones) can be exchanged against each other. Currencies can be classified as either floating currencies or fixed currencies based on their exchange rate regime.

e) Financial Institutions - In financial economics, a financial institution is an institution that provides financial services for its clients or members. Probably the most important financial service provided by financial institutions is acting as financial intermediaries.

Most financial institutions are highly regulated by government. Financial institutions provide service as intermediaries of financial markets. They are responsible for transferring funds from investors to companies in need of those funds. Financial institutions facilitate the flow of money through the economy.

f) Distribution of wealth – is a comparison of the wealth of various members or groups in a society. It differs from the distribution of income in that it looks at the distribution of ownership of the assets in a society, rather than the current income of members of that society.

g) Jurisprudence – Jurisprudence is the theory and philosophy of law. Scholars of jurisprudence, or legal theorists (including legal philosophers and social theorists of law), hope to obtain a deeper understanding of the nature of law, of legal reasoning, legal systems and of legal institutions. Modern jurisprudence began in the 18th Century and was focused on the first principles of the natural law, civil law, and the law of nations. General jurisprudence can be broken into categories both by the type of question scholars seek to answer and by the theories of jurisprudence, or schools of thought, regarding how those questions are best to be answered. Contemporary philosophy of law, which deals with general jurisprudence, addresses problems in two rough groups:

Problems internal to law and legal systems as such.
Problems of law as a particular social institution as it relates to the larger political and social situation in which it exists.

h) Sociology – Sociology is the study of society. It is a social science-a term with which it is sometimes synonymous-which uses various methods of empirical investigation and critical analysis to develop and refine a body of knowledge about human social activity. For many sociologists the goal is to conduct research which may be applied directly to social policy and welfare, whilst others produce purely academic theory closer to that of philosophy. Subject matter ranges from the micro level of individual agency and interaction to the macro level of systems and the social structure. Sociology is a very broad discipline. Its traditional focuses have included social stratification, social class, social mobility, religion, secularization, law, and deviance. As all spheres of human activity are sculpted by social structure and individual agency, sociology has gradually expanded its focus to further subjects, such as health, medical, military and penal institutions, the Internet, and even the role of social activity in the development of scientific knowledge.

i) Statistics - Statistics is the study of the collection, classification, analysis, and interpretation of data. It deals with all aspects of this, including the planning of data collection in terms of the design of surveys and experiments. It is used to understand the distribution of society in terms of physical, financial and mental health.

j) Psychology is the science of behavior and mental processes. Its immediate goal is to understand individuals and groups by both establishing general principles and researching specific cases. For many, the ultimate goal of psychology is to benefit society. In this field, a professional practitioner or researcher is called a psychologist, and can be classified as a social scientist, behavioral scientist, or cognitive scientist. Psychologists attempt to understand the role of mental functions in individual and social behavior, while also exploring the physiological and neuro-biological processes that underlie certain functions and behaviors. Psychology incorporates research from the social sciences, natural sciences, and humanities, such as philosophy.

Like this Science has taken hundreds of forms and transforming lives of individuals in thousands of ways. Science is a result of human’s mental faculty. Application of Science is fruit of human efforts. Everyday hundreds of researchers, scientists, technologists are constantly experimenting and innovating taking forward Science as a discipline. If we look at advancements and revolution taking place in lives because of technological progress happening in countries of Europe, America, Japan and India one cannot undermine the human efforts. We can let go of such a Science but have to intelligently and cautiously make it a part of our life.

Our Devotion

Indians are natural devotees is a hackneyed opinion and we need to test this.

In our devotion what percentage constitutes Love and what percentage Fear? Love and Fear are two distinct and dissimilar things. Majority of peoples’ devotions is only Fear. For many of them temple is a shop or a business place; is a transaction with God. “Oh! God if you beget me a child, I will give you a silver cradle”; “If you help me get a pay rise, I will perform special prayers”; “ If you help my business prosper, I will render special offerings”; or “ God ! If you keep my secret intact I will hold a car festival”; “If you make my neighbor lose his pride I will serve you” – this tit for tat, eye for an eye kind of devotion is what most people have. If one God does not yield to their terms and conditions they move on to a different God, whoever favors their transaction. The inner heart lacks pure love; it is born out of fear. It is only to appease God in fear that something evil or bad might occur disrupting our daily routines and activities.

True devotion is unconditional and does not anticipate anything in return. Does mother expect anything in return from her child? Just as the Mother’s face beams with joy and contentment on seeing her child’s face, as the bird takes its flight with happiness at the dawn, as we get immersed and get lost on listening to good music, as our mind glows at the sight of a marvelous beauty; so is the devotion when mind meditates on God uninterrupted with other thoughts to experiences happiness. Such devotion is neither easy nor easily attainable. It is a result of rigorous and lengthy practice. It requires true detachment, wisdom and practice of righteousness. It constrains thoughts of personal comfort. It encourages thinking about miracles created by God in this ecosystem and how to fit and live in this ecosystem.

To fit and gel in this ecosystem is itself blossoming of soul. That is the secret of custom. Home, Family, Society, State and so on are all arrangements for the practice of such a custom.

Path for Blossoming of Soul

We have already looked at the summary of preaching of Upanishads and Bhagvad Gita. The purpose and goal of all those are:

“Any human being who considers all living things as embedded in him and acts indiscriminately and who sees the same spirit that is inside him to be in all living beings and becomes a partner in their experiences is free of sorrow and sin.”

All troubles and issues arise when one has a differentiative treatment towards his fellow beings. A person who experiences oneness among all living beings will not have enemies.

Such an encompassing and inclusive thought can be well appreciated but difficult to bring into practice. Such a daunting uphill task has to be scaled step by step which means it is attainable and can be fully realized only through daily observance. In that observance our mind, intellect and ears will have to synergize for blossoming of the higher and most sensitive, soul strength. That which human beings keep addressing as “I, Myself” is the soul.

If we stand by side of a pond and throw a stone to the center of pond, ripples are created at center which circumferentially traverses to the pond. Our soul also has to gradually expand in a wave form and cover the entire universe. That is blossoming of soul.

We can assume the waves to be prominently six in number and they are:

Home or Family – This is the first step of expanding of our Soul. It starts with melting of “Aham” (I or me) to spread and form mine (“attachment”) to include parents, spouse, children, relatives, well wishers, and friends. It will be a great refinement of mind if we practice to shoulder equally pains and pleasures that come to our family and in other walks of life. This will be the first wave.
Place of Work or Organization – Team or group that we form in our professional life. For a farmer it is his landlord and his co workers, customers for a businessman, students for a teacher, clients and judges for a lawyer so on and so forth for every individual there are several relationships that gets formed out of his profession. These relationships expand his attachment further and dilute the selfishness in him. Welfare which was earlier concerned to two or three is now shared with several people and life gets expanded. This is the Second Wave.
Place – From there welfare spreads, engulfing hundreds of people and making them a part of our rightful thought process. In such a movement the narrow mindedness of caste, creed, religion, class should dissolve and disappear from our lives. This is the Third wave.
State – From thereafter, attachment spreads to the State Level. We should incorporate the feeling that my fellow citizens are part of my family and fill our minds and hearts. There should not be any scope for any pride in one’s religion, caste, creed and class. Language, Literature, Knowledge, Culture and other important subjects should gain importance and should invoke a felling that all people residing in this state are one. This is the Fourth Wave.
India as a Country – Our expansion of mind should not stop at the state level but has to reach the entire nation. This is our birth country, irrespective of the state, city, language, religion, caste, creed; we are first citizens of the country and then the smaller classifications such as Hindu, Kannadiga etc. In the holy river of Indian all our differences have to get washed away. This is the Fifth Wave.
Human race – Our love towards our country needs to further expand and flow to cover the entire human race. Ignoring the development of others, India’s development cannot take place and without development of India there cannot be progress for any other state or region. Without development of State there cannot be welfare of city, society or family. If we segregate and observe, a human’s life which appears miniscule and the gigantic human society has an orderly relationship like a chain. Let alone the human kingdom, all living beings should enter our ecosystem. That is compassion, repentance, kindness. That is feeling of being part of universe and that is the mark of supremely intelligent.

In view of this, our ancestors said “Udaracharithananthu Vasudaiva Kutambakam” meaning for People with larger purpose in life and higher conduct the entire world is their family which is the sixth wave.

Our soul has to blossom like a flower with seven petals. That is true expansion of one’s life form or growth of soul. But the fact is in us most of the times the attachment and affection does not cross the boundary of our household. First our family and then the relatives will be the limit to which our thinking about society can extend. Our selfishness does not melt and flow beyond this. Our expansion of soul and inclusive attitude freezes at our door step. What is the use of our Vedanta being of highest order? We have confined our lives to self pity and compassion. Let alone our thinking about the entire world, we don’t even think about our city, state or country.

We have explored and found various reasons and causes for India to come under foreign rule. Another important reason for this is our narrow mindedness. We lack the practice of thinking about welfare of society; it appears that we undertake any social responsibility tasks (such as building shelter for underprivileged, hospitals, planting trees) more in anticipation of obtaining safe place in heaven or obtain a clean image in society rather than born out of self drive to do something better for the ecosystem we live in. People who do not get adequate respect and status in this world do not get mind to attempt to do anything for others. Our ancestors discarded the thinking about this world as something mean. Naturally thoughts about our city or village, state, nation all vanished from our minds. “Thinking about the city, wealthy person became poor” with this opinion our people lost the national pride. This led to downfall of our society. We left the concern about the village to the village head; state to the rulers or government of state. To the extent the Village head or rulers of state were efficient citizens obtained well being. If the governors of villages and state were useless and inappropriate the citizen’s welfare worsened. Our ancestors did not define rules and principles for governors of state to appropriately deliver their responsibilities. They believed more on the ruler’s self commitment to righteousness. They did not see any reason for not keeping faith in their governors. But in our era there is higher and urgent need to have a good governing system to monitor the functioning of our Heads of State or Nation. Democracy has been a great tool and weapon which we are gifted to voice our opinion and elect an able and efficient leadership but it is our important duty to exercise this collectively with right intellect.

Harmony – Balanced Approach

In our time the expansion in terms of geography is very much reduced. Distance between cities and states are getting bridged in all possible ways. Travel to places which was taking several months and days has been possible today in few days and few hours respectively. Communication has revolutionized our lives where we can get in touch and be in real-time contact across time horizons and geographies with people. We are virtually getting to be one single world with entire community networked. In Sunday Market of Tippedoddi village of Mulbagal Taluk, you can find clothes from England, knives from Germany, American automobiles, Australian Cotton, crackers from Japan, toys from China. As every city and village is getting globalized is it right for us to forget the huts and houses present here? We cannot forget nor neglect any strata of society in this development process.

We already have identified six strata of our society. In this context we need to always remember one principle. Smaller ones should not be obstacles for the larger ones; larger ones should not suppress the smaller ones. In our concern for our household we should not forget our city; for welfare of society we cannot split families. It would be similar to ill treating your wife in fear of your mother or expelling your mother based on complaint of your wife. For the benefit of caste and religion Nation cannot be subjected to loss and destruction. If the caste and region is getting destroyed we need not be silent on the pretext of Nation. There is no benefit in creating enemies for sake of nation and cannot allow our country to suffer in our admiration of Unified world.

The challenge of righteousness or dharma that is facing us is how to stratify our Love and devotion to each of the six strata discussed above. In our pursuit to reach zenith of our life; we cannot ignore any of the six steps as irrelevant; we cannot stop and stagnate at any stage. To orderly organize all of these is rightful thinking. This is called balanced approach or harmony.

Our food becomes nutritious only when various tastes and ingredients are included. Salt opposes sourness, spicy chilly is opposing to jaggery but all this put together turn out into a delicious dish. Cooking is a process of transforming all these substances to a state of co-existence and is nothing but harmony of tastes. In all our worldly transactions it is essential to have such wisely harmony.

To achieve this harmony it requires principle sensitive knowledge and that is true learning. There are many things that we want in this world. In that, what is the cost of each of them? Which is more important to us? What is of top priority? - A balanced judgment has to be exercised and this knowledge is of supreme value to us. We already have seen different faculties of science and what we need to exercise on top of these is this balanced approach.

New Pot with Old Clay

I have mentioned before that empire of science is not without limitations. Science can capture all those which can come to experience of our senses. Metaphysical objects and their actions can be explained to an extent by Physics and Biology. The supreme energy that is behind Physics is completely unexplainable by science. For this reason we need to bear in our mind that there certain things which is beyond the boundary of science. This is because looking at the scientific inventions and discoveries, Scientists can over stretch themselves to believe that nothing is farfetched for it. Last few years the advancement of Science and Technology has been profound, the nuclear advancements, travel to moon and exploration of other planetary objects, information technology explosion and so on. This is going to continue further but one basic tenet has to be remembered that science is part of world nature and is not beyond nature, it is in fact child of it. We have been able to create all these miracles from the raw material and principles made available by nature; clay is the same the pot that is being molded is new; hands of the potter is still the same the wheel that is available to make pots is different. Science has not created any new sense or any new organ. Even if succeed to develop something new the basis of that still will be of the same clay. What comes to light from this is that Science is an effort to bring out all the hidden capabilities of ancient nature; but will not create new nature itself. Scientists unlike Supreme saint Vishwamithra have not taken a path to create a new form which did not exist earlier. Even Vishwamithra attempted to create a clone of four faced Brahma which is an act of copying but not originality. As the limitations of Science are of this nature, it is not wise to lose our intellect to newer scientific thoughts and discard the everlasting spiritual knowledge. There is no conflict between Science and Spirituality. There is no need for a Spiritual practitioner to accuse Science. Life looks complete and gets beautified when one blends Science and Spirituality; Science at level of transactions and Spirituality at level of thinking.

Beware of Westernisation

For many years now we have been influenced and attracted by the show off of the western society, there mannerisms, their dress sense, etiquette and food habits. That glittering make-up is giving way to fading faces. Behind the rosy lips there are unbrushed teeth; inside the perfume filled clothes are those bodies which have not seen water for a long time. Intoxicating food, deadly weapons are the wonders of science. Kill, Eat, Loot is becoming the mantra of many nations. If we scrape the civilization make-up we are seeing the behavior similar to that of wild animals. Civilized Face, Devil’s mind appears to be the progress of western world.

This no way suggests that the western civilization is filled with wrong things and no reason for us to consider all of them as evil. There are many courageous and brave accomplishments in them. In current Indian Society there are hundreds of practices and acts which are demeaning and derogatory. Our job is to carefully examine the both the societies, select and adopt best of them. In the acts of humans whether they belong to eastern or western world there are many weakness and lacuna natural to their character. Therefore there is no sect or society which can be supremely idealized. Every human creation is bound to be subjected to independent examination and research. That independent wisdom is our duty.

Spiritual world is not visibly present, does not give scope for anyone to argue that it is untrue. The power of our senses is limited is a fact known to everyone. Eyes cannot smell; ears cannot see forms; nose cannot hear sounds. Every sense organ has different capabilities. Those which are not accessible to eyes are accessible to nose, that which appears false to nose is confirmed as truth by ears; things which are said to be unseen by ears are seen by eyes. Something that is not identified by one sensory organ can easily identified by other. The field of influence of any sense organ is limited. Eye power of every individual is different if one has the capability to spot something that is there few inches away and some can spot few feet away. But no human eye can spot that is miles away. Same is the case with one’s ears. If one kind of music can bring out happiness and pleasure for certain group of people, the same can be boring and not so pleasant to others but no one can hear the naturally s produced sound few miles away. Therefore what can be true for sense organ can be totally false for other. All of us have different tastes and preferences, if one likes sweet; it might be completely distasteful to others. As we observe that the capabilities of every sense organ is distinct and limited; one cannot refute the claim that there could be things which are beyond the capabilities of these sense organs. For this reason, our ancestors believed that soul is something that is beyond our cognition and cannot be subjected to our examination and held Vedas as the supreme evidence. The great saints who had insights far deeper than our sense organs and Vedas formed their gospel of experience.

Debt to Nation

One of the common difference between us and citizens of the western world (referred to as England in the original book) is with reference to the constant recollection of our debt to nation. A citizen in the West fully acknowledges the privileges and support rendered to him by government and is cognizant that he has to receive more and in-return he has certain duties that he needs to perform is something that always stays in his memory. In our case the fact that we need to bear in mind that we are indebted to nation is itself something that is not well received by us. Our righteousness and duty does not cross the boundary of our house. We need to earn well; need to leave property for our wife and children and need to be comfortable in our houses is our thought process. Our visit to temples and holy places is also to ensure that we bring welfare and wealth to our family. The thought of nation very rarely occurs to our mind. This is narrow minded thinking of our righteousness. Duty and responsibility towards family is big and of foremost importance. But that in itself is not the complete form of our righteousness and duty. A person who does not contribute or work for welfare of co-citizen is as good as being a defaulter of duty or righteousness.

A person who is bound to duty and has devotion to upliftment of soul needs to get involved in some form of social service. Pride of our duty has to flow beyond our house. Walls of our house should not become imprison our life. Our commitment to serve for one of the selfless cause will help us achieve the right fulfillment and true meaning for our life.

Like this the path to improve our souls is many fold. This is also the path to improve our nation. Our holy scriptures (Vedas) which advice us on the path of philosophy and our path to create comfortable and dignified life for the entire society are not mutually opposing. They are in fact two edges of the same road.

Blend of Old and New

We have discussed about the progress above. What is the path for it? What are the tools and methods for it? – is difficult to analyze and comprehend. Presently in the world obstacles which were never seen earlier have taken birth. In the human history this has been period of transition. Even in that the obstacles that are posing human minds of Indians is not being posed to any other country. The reason for this is the dilemma of our ancient customs and rituals vis a vis western influence on our civilization.

In two centuries that preceded our independence, our lifestyle had been adulterated. In the many tools and machines that Europeans introduced to India, the magic wound by some of the materialistic luxuries had been very attractive. Their strategy and equipments of warfare helped them win over many Indian states. We lost our mind to their display of valor and strength. It cast a illusion in our minds that Western Civilization is much bigger and their lifestyle is of higher order. Their way of dressing, food and entertainment, their teaching methodologies, their mannerisms – all were falsely considered by us to be better than ours and we gave up our customs and practices. So do we have to really want to become like Westerners? Just look at them and their lifestyle – there is lot of unrest everywhere, houses have become transit lounges, marriages have become contracts, whatever we like has become dharma or righteousness, husband and wife, parents and children relationship are falling apart, enmity between nations; racial discrimination and various such differences. There is fear of war, anxiety about food for common man, jealousy and uncertainty cloud in many parts of western world. Can we call this as a good civilization? Is destruction of peace feature of civilization?

By asking these questions we are not suggesting everything in Western Civilization is bad. There are many noteworthy aspects of western progress. There are many things which strengthen and nourish human life that has been earned by westerners. In spite of these accomplishments there are many things which are beyond their reach is the point to be borne in our minds.

Such an open criticism is possible with respect to Indian culture as well. Whatever principles of life our ancestors have found for good life are proving to be insufficient. We can remove this insufficiency by drawing many points from western culture. Westerners need to learn from Indians and Indians need to learn from Westerners. Through this mutual learning process there could be betterment of human life.

One of the primary questions that is with respect to India is how to blend our ancient culture with that of the new culture of Western countries. How do we evolve a path that is favorable to our progressive path and at the same time does not make detached from our ancient history? It is not appropriate to blindly ape the Westerners without having an independent thinking of their practices. It is not a path which is of contentment and satisfaction is quite evident from their current state. At the same time it is unjust and inappropriate to completely give up the Western Culture as we all of have become part of one single globalized world. We have shredded the image and practices of brahminical attitude of staying aloof from rest of world. Those days are now behind us and will never return. Today’s world is a globalized market with connectivity across the world. We need to live with the other nations and we have identified that Western world has abundant source of valuable aspects for us. Their Science and Technology, their political and social strategies and more importantly their nature of independent thinking are some of them that needs to be absorbed by us.

But, how do we blend these new things with our old practices and customs? How do we ensure that the flow of Science and technology happens from the Western world without flow of their social practices? How do we ensure that their fascination to enjoy the materialistic things of life does not blind us from spiritual introspection? These are some of imposing questions that we face. The scope of this book is not to discuss those things and find answers for them. We are just highlighting the challenges in this process.

Primarily the social system of Western world is constructed on materialistic comforts. This does not mean that there have not been Saints and Sages in these places. Saints and Devotees equally exist there. But the political and economic system is strengthened because of consumerism and materialistic benefits they derive.

People like those are not rare in our society. India is a place of only saints is something that no one can claim. People here are increasingly getting attracted to such materialistic comforts but if we just study our ancient culture and practices we can clearly understand that our path is distinct than that of the westerners. In our society the foundation of the social order and practices is on the human value system. Soul is greater than physical body. Achieving solace of the soul is higher than the physical pleasures. Empathy is higher than affection. Donating is higher than Earning. Righteousness is higher than Power. Indian culture stands on such a discretionary balance.

For human life both body and soul are important but which is higher than the other? “Soul First, Body is secondary” says the Aryan system. “Whether soul exists or not, body is strong enough and therefore we need to look after it well” is the Western thinking. For those who believe “Soul is supreme and body is for sake of soul” their valuation of body is limited. For them how do you accept and align to their life, the system built around comforts to satisfy the body is the question. To efficiently determine this, it is required to have a independent thinking.

In the Western Culture usually every person as a independent thinking which is personal to him. For us individual’s life is specially connected to society. Western marriages are primarily concerned with two individuals who are tying the knot. Indian marriages are generally related to welfare of the two families they represent. Ours is a socialistic society where as the Westerners is a capitalist society laying emphasis more on individual comforts rather than family values. Thus, in the primary vision of architecting the social structure itself we are different and therefore it does reflect similar feelings in other societal practices. Industrial revolution was the root cause for growth of their society; agriculture formed the basis for growth of our society. As the Western countries lost their mind to accumulation of wealth through trade neglecting agriculture their situation became like hen which found gems while searching for food grains. Most of the countries have lost the capacity to grow food grains and heavily import them. We have to look at ways and means of industrializing the nation without losing our focus on agriculture. This has to be exercised with caution. So, if there are ten things that needs to be learnt and adopted from other parts of the world there are equal number of things which should not be adopted.

We are currently in age where different thought process, different faiths and different opinions are driving minds of people in innumerable directions leading them to a state of confusion and illusion. During these times people need to be sharp with wisdom. If we give ears to people who shout loud, then we will continue to remain in confused state. We should not be carried away by the mesmerizing campaigns of few interest groups but have independent review and thinking to find way of righteousness.

Patience – Order

Today’s world is fast and on-demand mode. The moment it realizes and conceives something to be good it insists to have it on immediate basis. If they are not able to achieve that goal then their immediate reaction is: revolt; revolt is often unkindly, mob behavior and violent. To disrupt the existing order or system even before thinking of constructing new one is not the right thing to do. We start holding rich responsible for all the poverty and clean homes for all the untidy ones. These things are easier to do and make them like culprits for our situations. People who became rich were at some point poor and people fail to examine the reasons and their actions that made them wealthy. No one has the patience to perform root cause analysis of their situations and identify the underlying factors which shape up their lives. This also does not mean that everyone who is wealthy has accumulated it in the most just manner but it advocates examining the governing and political boundary of accumulating wealth. Any change in system should not be a knee jerk reaction due to frustration.

Society is a outcome of a long historic review; it differs from one nation to another based on the situations they have been through; in-depth research of human behavior; evaluation of explicit and implicit values. Any change that is affected without bearing these things in mind is like medical treatment becoming more horrifying than the disease itself. Human Society is an ancient building. Any attempt to rebuild and remodel has to be done with utmost caution or else in our effort to patch up one side of the wall we will bring down the other.

Any change or reform in our conduct occurs due to a new opinion. This happens only when the new opinion or feeling sinks into the mind of that individual and blends into their natural mannerisms and not otherwise. As the seed that is sown in the ground takes time to get nourished and grow into a tress so does a new opinion or thinking will take time to get deep rooted into individuals to become a part of their natural conduct. Therefore it is unjust to expect and believe than any new thought that we propose to others will be taken immediately and acted upon. When the sanctity of our thought gets proved and registered in their minds they will naturally acknowledge.